so people are possessed by a question
and
it's part of our nature to be possessed
by this question and so you can think
about this as an archetypal question if
if you like and the question is what are
we doing here
and you can ask yourself that in
relationship to this conference you're
here to search for meaning and to
understand what that might mean but you
also might ask yourself well why is it
that you have to be here for your search
for meaning why is that something that
drives human beings it isn't
characteristic for example of animals
they don't seem to question their
existence and so there's something about
the very nature of human being that
makes us feel as if something needs to
be set right when that's being discussed
historically it's been associated with
the term Redemption people are in need
of redemption in the modern age we talk
about positive psychology and we talk
about happiness which is a much weaker
word but our forefathers had a more
profound sense of the problematic state
of human existence and they use more
profound words and the idea that we have
a need for redemption is a more profound
idea human beings and I'm going to talk
mostly about human beings in the West
because that's the literature that I'm
most familiar with human beings in the
West have been meditating on the nature
of human being for thousands of years
perhaps ever since we became self
conscious which is another thing that
distinguishes us from animals and
another thing that drives our search for
meaning the consequence of this
meditation or one of the consequences of
this meditation has been the production
of a series of books that people know as
the Bible I realize years ago that
people saw the world through lenses of
belief and more recently it's been
demonstrated that that's actually
inevitable the
because you're a limited cognitive
processor you have to frame your
perceptions with beliefs what I learned
is that the belief systems that people
use to frame their perceptions have a
structure and that structure is
religious it's a religious
presupposition is one that you you might
even know not notice that you make it's
a it's a predicate or an axiom or an
assumption and the study of those
axiomatic assumptions is what religion
is about and one of your axiomatic
assumptions for example is that life
involves a search for meaning and that's
associated with the idea of redemption
and you you'll notice that you asked
that question because of course you're
here but you might not notice how
strange it is that all of you asked that
question and the fact that all of you
asked that question that human beings
have asked that question for as far back
as we can understand is indicative of
something profound about human nature
its lack of completion now I'm going to
walk you through the series of stories
that make up this library of books known
as the Bible because it presents a
theory of redemption that in a sense is
emergent it's a consequence of this
insanely complicated cross generational
meditation on the nature of being it's
not designed by any one person it's
designed by processes that we don't
really understand because we don't know
anything about how books are written
over thousands of years or what forces
caused them to be compiled in a certain
way or what narrative direction they
tend to take now one of the things
that's strange about the Bible given
that it's a collection of books is that
it actually has a narrative structure it
has a story and that story's being
cobbled together it's like it's emerged
out of the depths it's not a top-down
story it's a bottom-up story then I
suppose that's why
many of the world's major religions
regard the Bible as a book that was
revealed rather than one that was
written it's a perfectly reasonable
presupposition that it's revealed
because it's not the consequence of the
work of any one author it's not written
according to a plan or not a plan that
we can understand but nonetheless it has
a structure it also has a strange
structuring that it's full of stories
that no one can forget but that also
that no one can understand and the
combination of incomprehensible and
unforgettable is a very strange
combination and of course that
combination is basically mythological so
I'm going to start out by telling you my
genesis has to say about why it is that
you need to search for meaning now
people are pretty familiar as a general
rule with basic stories in Genesis
Genesis starts out with the Word of God
creating being from chaos that's a very
complicated idea the idea is that
whatever the word is which is logos from
a from a Christian perspective from a
Western perspective that logos which is
something like consciousness and
something like speech has the power to
pull order out of an underlying chaos
now we do this all the time people do
this all the time that's I suppose in
some sense why we're hypothetically made
in the image of God we use our
consciousness to constantly construct
being out of chaos and according to the
initial opening of Genesis there's
something about that that's akin to the
construction of the world so that means
that from the perspective of this book
consciousness itself plays a world
constructing role it's got a central
place and human beings in some sense
parties participate in that in some
minor sense I suppose but in a sense
that none nonetheless makes them akin to
what the library of books called the
Bible assumes his deity and once God
logos extracts order out of chaos he
builds a little world and he populates
it
and then in the little world he puts a
garden a walled garden that's paradise
because paradise means walled garden or
Eden and Eden means well watered place
and you might think well why a garden
and the answer to that is a garden is
the optimal combination of nature and
culture or chaos and order because a
garden is where nature flourishes but
it's also where nature flourishes in a
in a safe and controlled environment so
that's like an optimal environment for
people and so there's a garden God puts
the people in there and that's optimal
when he warns them he says this is a
strange thing he says well now you're in
the garden that's where you should live
and there's something you shouldn't do
and what you should do is eat a
particular fruit now I'm going to tell
you something about vision human beings
have excellent vision first of all we
see color
hardly any creatures see color but we do
and not only do we see color but our
vision is tremendously acute the only
other animals that can see as well as us
are birds of prey for mammals man we can
see like you wouldn't believe and the
and for primates as well as we can see
much better than our closest primate
relatives and why that is is a bit of
mystery but there's a woman in in
California who seems perhaps to have
solved that her name is Lin Isabel and
she was very interested in how human
beings developed vision and she's
interested in patterns of predation
predator-prey relationships and she knew
that our tree dwelling ancestors
millions of years ago were frequently
preyed upon by snakes in fact there's
some evidence that our tree dwelling
ancestors and snakes Cole evolved and
that our visual system is particularly
good at picking up the patterns of
camouflage that snakes used to hide in
trees or in the undergrowth and what is
Bell showed was that if you looked at
primate populations around the world
where there were more predatory snakes
the primates could see better it's a
very high correlation and so she
concluded that the reason that human
beings can see so well is because of
snakes
now she thought the association between
that and the snake story in Genesis was
interestingly coincidental but it's much
more than that you know we don't know
how the Adam and Eve story came about we
know it's very ancient but there's
something about it that sticks in our
memory and in our culture and the reason
for that seems to be that in some
strange way it's an extraordinarily
accurate summation snakes gave us vision
what about fruit now the reason we can
see colors is because our visual system
evolved to detect ripe fruit what about
women well you have to be pretty wait
code smart a woman so there's this weird
interconnection in Genesis between women
fruit and snakes an idea is that the
interplay between the three remember
women are gatherers - or were gatherers
historically speaking and they shared
food with men and that's a strange thing
because human being share food and
hardly any other animals do and so women
did tempt men with fruit and they didn't
make them self-conscious along with this
Nathan the fruit and that was a
catastrophe what happens in Genesis is
that when people become self conscious
when they eat the fruit their vision
improves the scales fall from their eyes
and all of a sudden they can see in a
way that no other animal has ever seen
and one of the things they can see is
that they're naked and that that's a big
problem and you might ask well what does
being naked mean and that's quite
straightforward people often dream for
example of being naked in front of a
crowd and to be naked in front of a
crowd is to have all your frailties and
vulnerabilities revealed to judgment
that's a nightmare for people and so to
become self-aware is to wake up into a
nightmare
and the nightmare involves two profound
realization of individual vulnerability
and the consequence of that in genesis
is that people are banished from
paradise and are from then on in need of
redemption and that they have to work
and that's how man comes to be in a
fallen state and you don't have a need
for redemption or need for meaning your
request after meaning unless you're in a
fallen state and everyone strangely
enough has this intuition that they're
in a fallen state that something is
wrong with the world that needs to be
put right and more than that or
something is wrong with being it needs
to be put right and more than that that
in some weird sense weird way they have
a moral obligation to participate in
that process and that drives us like
it's beneath what drives us it's an
axiomatic presupposition the next thing
that happens in Genesis is that Abel and
Cain are born and they're really the
first two human beings because Adam and
Eve are made by God where's Kane and
Abel are born there they're the first
people that are born in history and
interestingly enough what happens
between Cain and Abel which is jealous
resentment against God followed by
murder is the first pattern of behavior
that human beings manifest once they
become self conscious that's an awful
story and it's a prototypical story in a
sense because what it says is that there
are two patterns of reaction to tragic
self consciousness and one is associated
with a murderous state of resentment
resentment towards life the kind of
murderous resentment that drove the
killer in Colorado for example murderous
resentment against life and the other
typifies bi-able
has something to do with the
establishment of the antithesis of
murderous resentment so you can
associate murderous resentment in a
sense with Hell and you can associate
Abel's path his choices with heaven and
so what happens is that as soon as
people become self conscious being
divides into
domain that has hell on one Expo on one
end in heaven on another and that's what
we hinted at in the in a second story in
Genesis after that everything dissolves
into a flood that's Noah into a flood
nature comes in tears everything down
and the Tower of Babel is erected and
that's a meditation on pride people
build a structure that reaches up to
where God is it's a presumptuous act and
there's a reason for that too one of the
consistent warnings that emerges in the
biblical writings is warnings against
the sin of pride and the sin of pride is
an intellectual sin and it's associated
with the presupposition that you know
enough to do without the transcendent
and the biblical stories state very very
clearly continually that that is
catastrophic ly dangerous that you
always have to be aware that there's
something transcendent that supersedes
the domain of your knowledge and and and
what what might you think of people who
who don't believe that and they're
totalitarians because they believe that
their belief is total and we know what
happens when people become totalitarian
what happens is you get the instant
creation of something on earth that very
closely resembles hell and that was
hammered home into 20th century if you
want to derive one lesson from the 20th
century it's that totalitarian States
and totalitarian ideologies are not a
good way to entrap or or search after
meaning that's a mistake
after the flood the flood is before the
flood that's prehistory that's so far
back in time we can't even imagine it
after the flood there's a there's a new
beginning in a sense and that's when
history really starts from a biblical
perspective and the way the Old
Testament lays itself out then is that
it's kind of a classic hero myth a hero
methods associated with the
establishment of States and generally
speaking when when societies mythologize
the beginning of their state they
imagine a set of heroes it's sort of
happening with people like George
Washington in the United States it
happens automatically that the founders
of the state are the state are
mythologized
as the great heroes of the past it's the
great heroes of the past our forefathers
who established the state and of course
that's true and there were millions of
them but you can't tell a story about
millions of people so all the actions of
those millions of people are collapsed
and condensed and compressed and turned
into a kind of fiction that's more real
than truth that describes the patterns
that characterize how the state was
founded and the old testament runs us
through that the heroes like Abraham for
example and Jacob who are crucially
involved in the establishment of the
polity of the actual state but something
always happens as this state is
established and what happens is the
state's established and then people get
off course and the leadership gets off
course and then the state collapses into
a state of chaos and then there's a
prophetic revelation warning of that
danger and then there's a terrible
period of chaotic disruption and then
there's the regeneration of the state
that story is foreshadowed in the Old
Testament by Exodus Moses story Egypt's
a tyranny a leader rises to pull
everyone out of tyranny there's a
terrible chaotic interlude the wandering
in the desert and then there
is the reestablishment of the state
that's an archetypal pattern that
happens to all of you it happens to
every country the pattern is there in
your system of belief which is yours in
the collective belief and something
arises like a snake analogous to a snake
to disrupt it because the state is
insufficiently adapted to the
environment it doesn't have all the
answers it ages and becomes corrupt and
then it's prone to collapse and that
collapse is a catastrophe
a chaotic catastrophe that happens to
you every time for example that your
dreams are shattered or that you
encounter a great tragedy it happens to
people when their spouse dies or when
they're diagnosed with a very very
dangerous illness or when their children
are damaged that event analogous as I
said to a snake and that's partly
because the circuits in your brain that
detect snakes that other animals use 2d
techniques are the same circuits that we
use to detect things that go wrong and
things are always going wrong for us and
we're always collapsing into a state
where we're wandering through a desert
in a desert is a state that's bereft of
meaning and bereft of ideas and in that
state then we're desperately seeking for
well for the establishment of another
state and a state that we hope will be a
better state it'll be like the last
state except there'll be more to it and
everyone will finally be happy in that
that's part of our utopian dream and
it's impossible not to be in that story
you're either in a state of order or
you're in a state of chaos that's where
the Daoists for example believe that the
world is made out of order in chaos
because you're always in one of those
two places what happens in the old
testament is that the limitations of the
state itself start to become apparent
and they become apparent in that the
state is established but it always
collapses and then it's reestablished
but it always collapses it's never
permanent and there's repetitions of
this continual repetitions of the
a knop shot of the Old Testament at
least the way that it's been constructed
in Christianity is that the state itself
is flawed it cannot provide the final
answer to the question what constitutes
genuine Redemption well this is an
important issue it's important issue
psychologically it's an important issue
politically is the state the final
answer well it's a totalitarian claim we
know that it was claimed by people like
Stellan it was certainly claimed by the
communists it was claimed by people like
Hitler that the state was the final
answer it still claimed in many ways in
places like China today the individuals
subsumed underneath the state
organization in the state well under
Stalin the state was already in a state
of perfection if you complained about
its imperfection then you were going to
be killed so the idea that the state is
perfect although it's a tremendously
flawed idea can be pursued so hard by
people who are gripping their narrow
viewpoints that the state itself becomes
murderous the old testament sort of sums
itself up in the book of Job and it's a
problematic summing up because job is
tormented in all sorts of ways
everything that could possibly be
terrible that happens to any person
happens to job they can't understand why
so job is in like a final state of
unredeemed being the state's not the
answer
well so then if being is order being is
chaos and chaos is intolerable and the
state order is not the answer what do
you have left that's the question the
new testament attempts to solve one of
the problems with with the Soviet Union
for example was their inability correct
errors see when you we start out with an
a priori hypothesis about what
constitutes the truth and that
structures your life it's very difficult
to make the kind of micro Corrections
that
has to make on a continual basis in
order to remain dynamic and fluid so in
order to stay adapted to reality not
only do you have to have a viewpoint but
you have to engage in a process of
modifying that viewpoint and the way
that you engage in the process of
modifying that viewpoint there's two
ways really one is continual minor
adjustments as a consequence of paying
attention so for example if you're
having a conversation with your wife or
a friend or maybe it's a difficult
conversation there's a couple of ways
that conversation can go one is you can
take your viewpoint and you can impose
it on that person and often when people
are talking that's what they're trying
to do they're not having a conversation
what they're doing is attempting to
impose a viewpoint that they already
hold their own the person that's
listening and if they're a tyrant or a
bully they'll do that and pay no
attention whatsoever to the person's
response and in fact they'll get
irritated and even violent if the person
doesn't accept their a priori framing is
there an alternative well there is an
alternative the alternative is to pay
attention and to listen on the off
chance that the person that you're
talking to might tell you something you
don't know but in order to listen you
have to be already convinced that the
little theory that you're using to
orient yourself in the world isn't good
enough because if it was good enough
then why would you bother listening so
you have to be deeply aware of your own
ignorance and that's what humility means
humility means to be deeply aware of
your own ignorance it doesn't mean to
slink around in a shamed manner it means
to make the presupposition that you may
still have something left to learn and
that this annoying person in front of
you might have something to teach you if
you would just listen and so you're
discussing a problem and a problem is a
time when the things you think aren't
working that's what constitutes a
problem so you have a little problem and
you're discussing it let's say with your
wife and she offers you her opinion and
you can brush it off and in which case
your little state stays intact it
doesn't move it's still made out of
stone it's pillars and you're still a
tyrant or you can listen you can think
oh I see there's a micro correction that
I need to make in one of the peripheral
elements of my belief and that's a
little painful
because it means you have to let
something go your your presumption and
then you have to be a little chaotic as
you adjust to the new information and
then you have to reconstitute yourself
and what that means interestingly enough
is that you have to make a sacrifice and
godlike sacrifices especially if they're
of the proper kind and the proper kind
of sacrifice is the one that you made of
your micro belief when you're faced with
evidence of error and if you make those
sorts of micro sacrifices then God stays
pleased with you and the reason for that
is that your models of the world stay up
to date now one of the things that
happens in the Old Testament all the
time is that people are making
sacrifices to God and modern people they
just have no idea what like why does God
want burnt lamb smoke it's it's not
obvious to modern people but you know
your ancestors weren't stupid
they were dramatizing something they
were dramatizing this tremendous
realization that no other creature has
ever managed which is that there are
things you can do to your being that
changed the nature of reality and if you
do them properly you can make reality
better it's mind-boggling and they acted
that out because they didn't really
understand it they noticed that if
things weren't going right you had to
sacrifice something valuable and that
seemed to make God happy well you might
have been a firstborn calf or a
firstborn son for that matter for modern
people it's more like an idea you have
to sacrifice an idea that you hold dear
in order to progress because the idea is
that you hold dear are exactly what are
making you suffer if you're suffering so
you have to sacrifice them and then you
have to let them go and the consequence
of that is that you enter into this
little period of chaos and then maybe
you pop out of that and that's a good
thing and so here's an interesting
observation that process of being in the
state and identifying an error and
correcting it that's a little death and
rebirth that's like the Phoenix the
Phoenix dissolves itself into ashes and
then pops back up as a new bird
in the New Testament there's this weird
idea for that you have to identify with
a person who continually dies and is
reborn or what does that mean it means
that the idea that Redemption itself is
not the consequence of being in a state
it's the consequence of participating in
a process and the process is the
willingness to continually have yourself
sacrificed chaotic and then reborn and
that's what keeps things alive now in
the in the passion story there are other
elements and the elements are important
so for example the story of Christ is
predicated on the assumption that the
person who is making the ultimate
sacrifices performs another number of
Acts or undergoes a number of processes
and one is a disciplined apprenticeship
so for example in order to have some
ideas that you can let go and then
reconstitute you have to have some ideas
you can't just be all chaotic and
uninformed and so in the New Testament
Christ is a master of tradition he's a
master of the law and you have to be
disciplined you have to be a master of
something before you're formed at all
you have to be imbued with the spirit of
your ancestors will say you have to take
on that that burden you see this
reflected in popular culture for example
in the movie Pinocchio at the end of the
movie when Pinocchio is about to become
a real boy his last challenge is to
rescue his father and he does that and
to rescue the father means to make peace
with your culture and to embody it but
then not to assume that that's absolute
it's a necessary process of discipline
the next idea that underlies the passion
ideas in the New Testament is that the
ultimate sacrifice is the sacrifice of
yourself
to God now that's a very strange idea
it's a very very sophisticated idea
because what happens in the Old
Testament is there's the constant
sacrificing of something else this
requires a different order of being what
does it mean to offer yourself up as a
sacrifice to God well if you think of
God as an ineffable representation of
the highest possible value that's what
monotheists presume henry presume god's
nameable and even the israelites presume
that God wasn't nameable it's ineffable
but it's the ultimate value whatever the
ultimate value is you don't know what it
is but you've got to have some idea and
the idea of offering yourself up as a
sacrifice to God is the same thing as
determining that your life will be
guided by unshakeable commitment to the
highest good and what that means is that
it's no longer your state that's in
charger it's no longer your ego that's
in charge it's not even you that's in
charge it means that your conversations
with people are no longer going to be
about convincing them that your
viewpoint is a right it means that what
your conversation is going to be about
in your speech is about attempting to
represent what you believe to be true in
the most concise and clear possible
manner no matter what and that's not how
people live people live in a sense by
it's like a conniving and the conniving
is a totalitarian conniving the
conniving is an idea that the world
should be the way that I want it to be I
have a theory about how I wanted to be
and I'm going to enforce that theory and
I'm going to be very angry when the
world doesn't respond the way I wanted
to and maybe I wouldn't be violent as a
consequence of it and I have some sense
of where I'm headed
maybe I'm headed for wealth for example
and I'm headed to an advertisement so
I'm with my wife when I'm 50 on you know
a tropical beach and that's how I'm
going to be redeemed it's a narrow and
totalitarian you point then I sacrifice
everything to that and it turns out that
that's a very bad idea because things
don't turn out the way I want them to
turn out
the alternative to that and this is part
of what happens in the Sermon on the
Mount which is very very strange
document because it represents a
transformation from the idea that
morality is constituted by adherence to
a set of rules to morality being aimed
at something that you might think about
as more of a positive good it's not
merely not doing what's wrong it's
something else
it's sacrificing yourself in the attempt
to make things better and and making
things better not by aiming at what's
better but by telling what's true and
assuming that if you do that then what's
better will happen whatever that is
because the thing is you don't know
what's better you don't have the
capacity to fully realize what would
constitute better we've seen that as I
said over and over in the twentieth
century people aim at a circumscribed
definition of what constitutes the
utopian state and all we get out of that
is endless hell we have to pursue what's
good but we don't know what's what
what's good is so how do we how do we
remove ourselves from that paradox well
it isn't a matter of gathering more
knowledge it's a matter of approaching
reality in a different manner and it is
an act of faith as Kierkegaard point to
code because if you decide for example
that you're going to pursue the highest
good whatever that is and the highest
good pursuing the highest good means
being willing to transform what your
conception of the highest good is you
pursue the highest good that's your aim
your aim determines the world you live
in we know that that's a fact that's a
psychological fact what you aim at
determines the nature of your world and
to aim wrong that's hard Amartya by the
way that's a greek word hamartia to aim
wrong that sin because Hammar Tiye which
is an archery term which means to miss
the target is what sin means so if
you're not in a state of grace it means
your aims wrong you know naming it the
right thing or maybe the world is
constituted badly and it's hell-bent on
torturing you that's the alternative
viewpoint so you got to get your aim
right you aim at the best and how do you
aim well the Sermon on the Mount says
something very interesting it says
once you get your aim right and you
decide to tell the truth then all you
have to do is concentrate on the day now
it's people read the Sermon on the Mount
like it's a hippy document you know be
like a flower be like a bird don't pay
any attention to the future you know
everything will be taken care of it it's
not that at all there's presumptions
that are nested in there and the
presumption is first of all that you're
aiming at a perfection you're ending up
whatever perfection is and you're not
trying to get other people to do that
you're aiming at it
you're reconstituting your actions and
your speech to aim at that and then you
do that by noticing very carefully and
attending to what constitutes the truth
and then you let that take you wherever
it will go and that's the sacrifice of
self to go on because you the truth is a
representation of whatever constitutes
reality your best attempt at whatever
constitutes reality and to follow that
means to follow something that's
transcendent because whatever reality is
it's certainly not something that you're
individually responsible for creating
even though you might participate in
that process to speak the truth is to be
guided by being it's a completely
different mode of being now I said right
after Adam and Eve's catastrophic
emergence into self consciousness the
world split into two attitudes one
associated with pain and the other
associated with Abell in that those
attitudes are associated with heaven and
hell well we know that human beings can
turn the world into hell if you're a
student of history you have no doubt
about that and no matter how terrible
you think the hell that people have
created in the past is if you read a
little more history you'll find
something even more terrible and people
of course are afraid of the human
capacity to turn things into hell that's
one of the things that underlies our
environmentalism we're afraid that our
misbehavior will turn the world into
help well be we believe we can do that
do we believe that human beings can turn
the world into heaven well that's a
harder thing to believe because there's
a lot more ways that things could go
wrong than there are ways that things
can go right so heaven is a much
narrower thing to aim at than hell which
is a chaotic mess well maybe it's
improbable but life is improbable that's
for sure and our unredeemed state of
being is improbable and the other thing
that's improbably is the burden that
we're required to carry existentially
we're it we're awake creatures of God
what does that mean it means that we
suffer and it's real that suffering and
it's not only that we suffer in that we
feel pain which is bad enough in
frustration and disappointment and all
the catastrophic things that are
associated with life but even worse we
can apprehend the possibility of that
recurring in the future
so even when none of those terrible
things happen to be happening right now
it's pretty easy for us to imagine that
they're going to happen tomorrow and
they will so not only can we imagine
that they're going to happen again
tomorrow they are going to happen again
tomorrow so we're in a state of constant
unredeemed suffering it's a big problem
and you know if you think about you
can't even imagine a state that would
address that it's just too big a problem
well so then there's another inference
in the new testament and its hypothesis
of a meta state and the inference is
that a life that's predicated on
constant death and renewal at every
level of being a life that's predicated
on a search for the truth and an attempt
to act out the truth and a life that's
associated with the sacrifice of self to
God produces a state of being that so
deeply meaningful that it justifies
suffering it doesn't eliminate suffering
there's no elimination of suffering
Nietzsche said he has he who has a why
can bear anyhow and what he meant by
that was
if what you're aiming at is of
sufficient profundity it's worth an
awful lot of misery to participate in
the process of bringing it about and
life has an unbearable depth of misery
and as a consequence it needs a an
absurd positive aim and the absurd
positive aim
that's posited in the New Testament is
participation in the process that
transforms earth into heaven the
generation of the kingdom of God on
earth and that actually means something
it means that the state of being that's
described by the parameters that I
already laid out the willingness to
engage in internal sacrificial death and
renewal and sacrifice of the self to the
highest value produces the state of
being subjectively that's associated
with habitation in the kingdom of God
and the actions that are conducted in
that state are what transform the
interpersonal state into the political
state that's a manifestation of that
kingdom now you all know this you know
this the same way that the people who
wrote the Bible know it because of
course people just like you wrote the
Bible and the Bible is about people when
you have a deeply meaningful
conversation with someone you change
them and you change yourself you know
that and the process that you're engaged
in well you have that deeply meaningful
conversation that's a mode of being and
that mode of being to the degree that
that of mode of being is predicated on
the attempt to communicate as
truthfully as possible and with the
highest possible end in mind then right
then and there you're in that state now
you can tell when you're in that state
because number one you're not
self-conscious time disappears number
two what you're engaged in is deeply
meaningful you don't bear the tragic
burden of your life at that moment
because what's happening with you is so
worthwhile that it consumes you
completely and people are in that state
to a widely varying degree but everyone
is in it sometimes when something like
that happens to you especially once you
learn to notice it you think well
there's nothing better than that
and if there's nothing better than that
then you might ask yourself why do
anything else now I've tried to figure
that out I've tried to figure that out
for years it's like because to me these
look like existential realities they're
not hypothetical States they're not
shoved off into some transcendent heaven
they're not otherworldly they're part of
being itself people can enter states of
heaven and hell and they can learn to
stay longer in one state or another so
why don't they stay in the best possible
state well one problem is the commitment
of faith I think it's very terrifying to
let go of the direction of your life and
say well I'm going to go wherever the
attempt to speak the truth will take me
because god only knows where you're
going to end up and it's certainly not
where you think in fact the willingness
to abandon going to where you think is a
prerequisite for doing this and so in a
sense you're you're a ship
that the wind takes wherever it wants to
take and the second problem I think is
that it's a real responsibility because
in order to undertake this process you
have to come to terms with the idea that
what you do in your life your wretched
miserable tragic prone life actually
matters really it matters you know when
people complain about meaninglessness in
their life all the time but I think
that's that's a kind of face-saving
illusion I think people are more afraid
of meaning than they are of
meaninglessness because meaningless
means meaninglessness means well I can
do whatever I want I mean it might be
kind of you know second-rate and might
be dull it might be dangerous it might
be destructive but it doesn't matter and
so I can do whatever I want to have no
responsibility because I don't mean
anything so I'm not responsible to
anything or anyone but if your life
actually has meaning and it doesn't
always have meaning it has meaning when
you're doing something that's meaningful
well then all of a sudden you are
responsible to a higher power so to
speak you're responsible to your own
soul and you're responsible to the state
of being that characterizes the world
itself and that's a massive massive
responsibility it's to take
responsibility in a sense it's to take
responsibility for the sins of the world
which is another prerequisite of the
mode of being that's described in the
New Testaments a very strange idea the
Redeemer takes on the sins of the world
what does that mean well it means all
human beings are Nazis and human beings
are the maoist red Garden human beings
are the slaughterers in Rwanda and
you're all human beings and so the take
on the sense of the world means to
realize that all those things that
characterize the human capacity to turn
earth into hell characterize you and
that in order to live properly you have
to live in
that addresses those elements of your
nature and again that's it
that's a terrible responsibility well
first of all who wants to admit that
second of all who can stand looking at
it and third who's going to take on the
burden of solving it well it better be
all of us or we're just going to keep
doing it so Redemption what does it mean
it means we're not in a state of grace
why it was self-conscious we're aware of
the owner of the tragedy of our being
we're unwilling to take full
responsibility for it or we're ignorant
about how to do that and that leaves us
bereft how do we solve that well we can
solve it with a state but the problem is
the state is not reliable it degenerates
into tyranny then it transforms into
chaos
then it reconstitutes itself and does
the same thing again it's not a good
answer is there another answer well
maybe I believe that what is outlined in
narrative form in the New Testament is
psychologically correct I believe that
the idea that endless micro death and
renewal produces a state of proper
adaptation to being and that the
prerequisites for that that are laid out
in the narrative structure that
underlies the New Testament are
fundamentally correct so to be redeemed
is to aim at the highest value to
sacrifice what's no longer useful and
valid in yourself and to tell the truth
and the consequence of that is existence
in a deep state of meaning that
justifies the tragedy of being and the
possibility of transforming your own
life in the most beneficial positive
direction
while simultaneously doing that for the
people around you and that's Redemption
thank you very much support Ontario's
public television donate at TV org